501 Blair Stone Road, Apt. 224, Tallahassee, FL 32301 | 850.591.9995 lesa@lekconsultants.com | linkedin.com/in/LesaEdwards

# **Human Resources Executive**

# Driving Leadership Development and Employee Engagement to Achieve Exceptional Organizational Results

Exceptional problem-solving skills and an outstanding ability to assess and mitigate organizational risk. Highly effective in influencing leaders to consider alternative solutions to the organization's most pressing challenges.

Well-documented record of developing a pervasive learning and employee engagement culture. Extensive experience in both union and non-union environments in the service and manufacturing industries.

# **Professional Experience**

National Foodservice, Inc., Atlanta, GA

Second-largest food distributor in the U.S., with 25,000 employees.

2010-Present

# Regional Human Resources Business Partner, Southeastern U.S. (2014-Present)

Drive leadership development and strategic planning with senior executives; collaborate with local HR teams on recruiting, employee relations, and policy development /enforcement for 1,800+ employees.

# Executive Coaching:

- Conducted talent assessment of all leaders within first 90 days; also collaborated with leaders to develop plans for high-potential employees including training, coaching, and on-the-job experience.
- Coached VP regarding an underperforming director—providing critical tools to clarify expectations and measure progress.
- Guided VPO through a departmental reorganization that resulted in enhanced productivity.

#### HR Leadership:

Played a key role in creating the Human Resources Business Partner Group, which transformed the HR structure from decentralized and transaction-focused to shared services.

#### **Division Vice President of Human Resources** (2012-2014)

Promoted to one of National's largest facilities, with 600+ employees including 350+ unionized warehouse and transportation employees, 175+ outside sales force, and administrative support personnel. Maintained relationships with five unions. Selected to be a regional diversity trainer.

# Company-Wide Leadership:

- > Launched an affinity group—Women in Foodservice—that helped develop and retain women.
- Launched a Go Green Team and attained Green Certification for the company, which gave the sales force a tremendous selling tool with customers ranging from Disneyland to local businesses.

#### HR Leadership:

- Implemented a new leave policy to manage absences more effectively and remove the burden of tracking from managers.
- Reduced worker compensation reserves \$1.5 M in one year through a combination of safety initiatives and partnering with medical groups and claims adjustors to resolve claims more rapidly.
- Partnered with sales VP to change recruiting approach to source a more qualified and diverse pool of new hires, which increased sales and improved market share.

#### Union Relations:

- Achieved long-term wins including breaking and creating practices during non-negotiation years in anticipation of the next negotiation year.
- Reduced number of clerical titles and classifications and blurred delineation of tasks despite union resistance, which resulted in greater efficiency, opportunities for cross training, and workforce reduction.

National Foodservice, Inc., continued

# **Division Vice President of Human Resources** (2010-2012)

Promoted to VP with 175 non-unionized warehouse staff and unionized drivers, as well as 150 administrative staff. Managed all 800-call complaints for the region.

# Union Relations:

- Prevented a formal union campaign by the warehouse group, which resulted in significant bottom-line increases, as non-union facilities average 1.5% higher EBITDA.
- Slashed union grievance filings 45% by conducting effective union contract management and ensuring meticulous documentation.

# Training & Culture:

- > Implemented an extensive training and development program focusing on managers first and then the hourly workforce in subsequent years.
- Transformed corporate culture with a new customer values campaign.

# Cannon Mills Cabinets, Atlanta, GA

2006-2010

Family-owned kitchen cabinet manufacturer, supplying home improvement centers such as Lowe's.

## **Corporate Human Resources Director**

As HR leader for 500-associate operations in three states, managed entire spectrum of HR, including policy development, benefits negotiations, employee relations, and recruitment.

- > Won a formal union campaign, which allowed the newest and largest facility to operate non-union.
- Developed and introduced a compensation and promotion program for manufacturing-line positions based on market research data, which improved ability to recruit and retain top talent.
- > Initiated and managed a training-grant program that included management development and personal skills for hourly workers.

# **Education & Professional Development**

University of Minnesota – Minneapolis Bachelor of Science in Management & Finance

Senior Professional in Human Resources (SPHR)

Certified Labor Relations Professional (CLRP)

**Development Dimensions International Certified Trainer** 

## **Professional Affiliation**

Taught SPHR/PHR prep course at Georgia State University

Society for Human Resource Management (SHRM)

Women's Foodservice Forum